Architecture is amazing, for sure.
毫无疑问，建筑学是很令人惊叹的。
It's amazing because it's art.
其原因在于，它是一门艺术。
But you know, it's a very funny kind of art.
不过这是一类非常有趣的艺术，
It's an art at the frontier between art and science.
交织了艺术和科学的前沿艺术。
It's fed by ...
它源自于…
by real life, every day.
真实的常日生活。
It's driven by force of necessity.
它受到了必要性的驱使。
Quite amazing, quite amazing.
非常，非常惊艳。
And the life of the architect is also amazing.
建筑师的生活一样很精彩。
You know, as an architect, at 10 o’clock in the morning,
要知道，作为一个建筑师， 早上十点的时候，
you need to be a poet, for sure.
你得当一个诗人。
But at 11,
但是十一点的时候，
you must become a humanist,
你又必须充满人文情怀，
otherwise you'd lose your direction.
否则你会变得迷茫。
And at noon, you absolutely need to be a builder.
但是下午的时候， 你又要做一个建筑工人。
You need to be able to make a building,
你需要能够建造楼房。
because architecture, at the end, is the art of making buildings.
因为建筑学，归根结底 是建筑的艺术。
Architecture is the art of making shelter for human beings.
建筑学是为人们建造庇护所的艺术。
Period.
目标明确。
And this is not easy at all.
这一点也不容易实现。
It's amazing.
会有很惊人的效果。
Look at this.
看看这个。
Here we are in London,
我们在伦敦，
at the top of the Shard of Glass.
在碎片大厦的顶端。
This is a building we completed a few years ago.
这是我们几年前完成的一个项目。
Those people are well-trained workers,
这些是受过培训的工人，
and they are assembling the top piece of the tower.
在组装塔的最高层。
Well, they look like rock climbers.
他们看起来就像是攀岩者。
They are.
他们的确是。
I mean, they are defying the force of gravity,
我的意思是， 他们在与重力做斗争，
like building does, by the way.
就像建筑物那样。
We got 30 of those people --
我们有30个这样的人——
actually, on that site, we got more than 1,400 people,
事实上，施工现场有超过1400个人，
coming from 60 different nationalities.
来自60个国家。
You know, this is a miracle. It's a miracle.
这是个奇迹，很不可思议。
To put together 1,400 people,
把1400个来自不同国家的人，
coming from such different places, is a miracle.
组合在一起，简直是奇迹。
Sites are miracles.
施工现场也很让人惊叹。
This is another one.
这是另一个。
Let's talk about construction.
我们来谈一谈施工。
Adventure, it's adventure in real life,
冒险，这是真实生活中的冒险，
not adventure in spirit.
不是精神上的。
This guy there is a deepwater diver.
这个人是深水潜水员。
From rock climbers to deepwater divers.
从攀岩者到深水潜水员。
This is in Berlin.
这是柏林。
After the fall of the Wall in '89,
在1989年柏林墙倒塌之后，
we built this building, connecting East Berlin to West Berlin,
我们建了这个建筑， 连接了东柏林和西柏林，
in Potsdamer Platz.
它位于波坦兹广场。
We got on that project almost 5,000 people.
有近5000人参与了这个项目。
Almost 5,000 people.
差不多五千人。
And this is another site in Japan,
这是另一个在日本的施工现场，
building the Kansai Airport.
位于关西机场。
Again, all the rock climbers, Japanese ones.
所有的攀岩者都是日本人。
You know, making buildings together
一起打造建筑物
is the best way to create a sense of cooperation.
是建立合作的最好方式。
The sense of pride -- pride is essential.
荣誉感，荣誉是核心。
But, you know, construction, of course,
不过理所当然的，施工也是
is one of the reasons why architecture is amazing.
为什么建筑学 令人惊叹的原因之一。
But there is another one, that is maybe even more amazing.
还有另一个理由，甚至更加惊艳。
Because architecture is the art
因为建筑学是艺术，
of making shelter for communities,
给社会创造庇护所的艺术。
not just for individuals --
并不为个人——
communities and society at large.
它造福于整个社区和社会。
And society is never the same.
社会群体的构成各不相同。
The world keeps changing.
这世界一直在变化。
And changes are difficult to swallow by people.
人们是很难理解这种改变的。
And architecture is a mirror of those changes.
而建筑就是这些变迁的镜子。
Architecture is the built expression of those changes.
建筑是这些变迁的表现。
So, this is why it is so difficult,
所以，这就是为什么它复杂高深，
because those changes create adventure.
因为这些改变创造了冒险。
They create adventure, and architecture is adventure.
它们本身就是一次次冒险， 然后它们又创造了冒险。
This is the Centre Georges Pompidou in Paris,
这是位于巴黎的乔治 · 蓬皮杜中心，
a long time ago.
很多年前的图片。
That was back in time, '77.
大概拍摄于1977年。
This was a spaceship landing in the middle of Paris.
这是在巴黎的中心的一个太空船。
Together with my friend in adventure, Richard Rogers,
我和我的朋友，理查德 · 罗杰斯，
we were, at the time, young bad boys.
我们那时候还是不良少年。
Young, bad boys.
年轻的混混。
(Laughter)
（笑)
It was really only a few years after May '68.
那是在1968年5月的几年后。
So it was a rebellion, pure rebellion.
发生了暴动，纯粹的暴动。
The idea was to make
其背后的动机是为了证明
the proof that cultural buildings should not be intimidating.
文化建筑不应该令人生畏。
They should create a sense of curiosity.
它们应该激发一种好奇心。
This is the way to create a cultural place.
这是一种创建文化场所的方式。
Curiosity is the beginning of a cultural attitude.
好奇心是文化态度的起源。
And there's a piazza there, you can see that piazza.
这里有一个广场。
And a piazza is the beginning of urban life.
广场是城市生活的开端。
A piazza is the place where people meet.
广场是人们见面的地方。
And they mix experience.
他们交流着彼此的经历，
And they mix ages.
打破了年龄的界限。
And, you know, in some way,
以某种方式，
you create the essence of the city.
你创造了城市的精髓。
And since then, we made, in the office, so many other places for people.
从那时起，我们 又设计了很多其他的建筑。
Here, in Rome, is a concert hall.
这里是罗马的一个音乐会大厅。
Another place for people.
另一个为大众服务的地方。
This building inside is actually designed by the sound, you can see.
这个建筑内实际上 是根据声音设计的。
It's flirting with sound.
声音在其中肆意徜徉。
And this is the Kansai Airport,
这个是日本的
in Japan.
关西机场。
To make a building, sometimes you need to make an island,
为了打造一个建筑， 有时你不得不建一座岛，
and we made the island.
于是我们就建了这么一座岛。
The building is more than one mile long.
这个建筑物的长度有一英里多。
It looks like an immense glider, landing on the ground.
它看起来像一个巨大的滑翔机， 降落在地面上。
And this is in San Francisco.
这是旧金山。
Another place for people.
另一个为服务大众的场所。
This building is the California Academy of Sciences.
这是加州科学博物馆。
And we planted on that roof --
我们在屋顶上种植了植物——
thousands and thousands of plants that use the humidity of the air,
成千上万的植物吸收空气中的水分，
instead of pumping water from the water table.
不需要从下方抽水浇灌。
The roof is a living roof, actually.
这个屋顶事实上是有生命的。
And this building was made Platinum LEED.
这个建筑是符合 LEED白金级认证标准的。
The LEED is the system to measure, of course,
LEED是一个用来衡量
the sustainability of a building.
建筑可持续性的系统。
So this was also a place for people
所以这也是一个 为人类服务的地方，
that will stay a long time.
将会持续运营很长时间。
And this is actually New York.
这个是在纽约。
This is the new Whitney,
这栋建筑是新惠特尼，
in the Meatpacking District in New York.
在纽约的肉类加工区。
Well, another flying vessel.
另一个飞船。
Another place for people.
另一个人文场所。
Here we are in Athens, the Niarchos Foundation.
现在我们看到的是雅典的 Niarchos基金会。
It's a library,
这是一个图书馆。
it's an open house, a concert hall
它是一个开放性建筑， 有一个音乐厅，
and a big park.
和一个大公园。
This building is also a Platinum LEED building.
这个也是白金级标准的建筑物。
This building actually captures the sun's energy with that roof.
这个建筑通过屋顶 使用太阳能供电。
But, you know, making a building a place for people is good.
打造以人为本的建筑物是件好事。
Making libraries, making concert halls,
建造图书馆，演奏厅，
making universities, making museums is good,
大学，博物馆都是很好的做法。
because you create a place that's open, accessible.
因为你建造了开放， 让所有人都能受益的地方。
You create a building for a better world, for sure.
毫无疑问，你建造房子是 为了让世界变得更好。
But there is something else
但是还有另外一个方面，
that makes architecture amazing, even more.
使建筑更加美好。
And this is the fact that
存在这样一个事实，
architecture doesn't just answer to need and necessity,
建筑学不只是为 需要和必要性服务，
but also to desires -- yes, desires -- dreams, aspirations.
还有欲望——是的， 欲望——梦想，愿望。
This is what architecture does.
这就是建筑学的作用。
Even the most modest hut on earth
即使是世界上最小的房子，
is not just a roof.
也不仅仅是为了遮风挡雨。
It's more than a roof.
它的作用超过了一个屋顶。
It's telling a story;
它在讲述一个故事；
it's telling a story about the identity of the people living in that hut.
讲述了曾经住在 那小屋的人的故事。
Individuals.
个人的故事。
Architecture is the art of telling stories.
建筑学是讲述故事的艺术。
Like this one.
就像这一个。
In London: the Shard of Glass.
伦敦的碎片大厦。
Well, this building is the tallest building in Western Europe.
这是西欧最高的建筑物。
It goes up more than 300 meters in the air, to breathe fresh air.
它高300多米，在上面 可以呼吸到新鲜的空气。
The facets of this building are inclined,
这座建筑的外观是倾斜的，
and they reflect the sky of London, that is never the same.
外墙会反射伦敦的天空， 景象千变万化。
After rain, everything becomes bluish.
下过雨后， 一切都变成偏蓝的颜色。
In the sunny evening, everything is red.
在晴天的下午， 一切都变成红色。
It's something that is difficult to explain.
这是一种难以言喻的感觉。
It's what we call the soul of a building.
我们把它叫做建筑的灵魂。
On this picture on the left, you have the Menil Collection,
这张图片的左侧是menil系列
used a long time ago.
很久以前所采用的。
It's a museum.
这是一个博物馆。
On the right is the Harvard Art Museum.
在右边的是哈佛艺术博物馆。
Both those two buildings flirt with light.
这两个建筑都能和光影巧妙地互动。
Light is probably one of the most essential materials in architecture.
光线或许是建筑中 最原始的材料了。
And this is in Amsterdam.
这个建筑位于阿姆斯特丹。
This building is flirting with water.
楼体和水面交相辉映。
And this is my office, on the sea.
这个是我的办公室，在海上。
Well, this is flirting with work.
不过它是在和工作调情。
Actually, we enjoy working there.
事实上，我们很享受在那里工作。
And that cable car is the little cable car that goes up to there.
小缆车把我们带到那上面。
That's "The New York Times" in New York.
这是纽约时报大厦，位于纽约。
Well, this is playing with transparency.
透明结构无处不在。
Again, the sense of light, the sense of transparency.
这个建筑再一次体现了 对光线和透明感的运用。
On the left here, you have the Magic Lantern in Japan,
在左边的图片，是“魔术灯”玻璃外墙，
in Ginza, in Tokyo.
在日本东京的银座。
And in the center is a monastery in the forest.
中间的是一座森林里的寺院。
This monastery is playing with the silence and the forest.
寺院，寂静，森林，三者和谐共处。
And a museum, a science museum.
（这张图是）一座博物馆， 科学博物馆。
This is about levitation.
主题是关于磁悬浮。
And this is in the center of Paris,
这个建筑是巴黎的中心，
in the belly of the whale.
在鲸鱼的肚子里。
This is the Pathé Foundation in Paris.
这是法国的Pathé基金会。
All those buildings have something in common:
这所有的建筑物都有一个共同点：
it's that something is searching for desire, for dreams.
一种追求欲望， 追求梦想的感觉。
And that's me.
那个人是我。
(Laughter)
（笑）
Well, it's me on my sailing boat.
在我的帆船上。
Flirting with breeze.
和海风调情。
Well, there's not a very good reason to show you this picture.
好吧我承认，这并不是 一个展示照片的好借口。
(Laughter)
（笑）
I'm trying, I'm trying.
我尽力了。
You know, one thing is clear: I love sailing, for sure.
不过很明显， 我喜欢扬帆出海。
I actually also love designing sailing boats.
我实际上也爱设计帆船。
But I love sailing, because sailing is associated with slowness.
我喜欢帆船， 因为帆船和慢节奏有着联系，
And ...
以及…
and silence.
以及沉默。
And the sense of suspension.
悬浮的感觉。
And there is another thing that this picture says.
照片还告诉了我们另外一件事。
It says that I'm Italian.
它揭露了我是意大利人。
(Laughter)
（笑）
Well, there is very little I can do about that.
这我可没办法。
(Laughter)
（笑）
I'm Italian, and I love beauty.
我是意大利人，我追求美感。
I love beauty.
我对美感十分着迷。
Well, let's go sailing, I want to take you sailing here,
我们可以乘船出发， 我想要带你们去
to this place,
这个地方，
in the middle of the Pacific Ocean.
在太平洋的中心。
This is the Jean-Marie Tjibaou Center.
这是Jean-Marie Tjibaou中心，
It's for the Kanaky ethnic group.
属于卡耐基民族。
It's in Nouméa, New Caledonia.
位于新喀里多尼亚的努美阿。
This place is for art.
这是一个为艺术所生的地方。
Art and nature.
艺术和自然。
And those buildings actually flirt with the wind,
这些建筑和微风，和信风
with the trade winds.
彼此依恋。
They have a sound, they have a voice, those buildings.
它们有声音，这些建筑会发声。
I'm showing this because it's about beauty.
我展示这张图片， 是因为它关乎美。
It's about pure beauty.
纯粹的美。
And let's talk about beauty for a moment.
现在我们来讲一下美。
Beauty is like the bird of paradise:
美就像是天堂鸟：
the very moment you try to catch it, it flies away.
在一个瞬间你试图抓住它， 可是它却飞走了。
Your arm is too short.
你的胳膊还不够长。
But beauty is not a frivolous idea.
但是美并不是一个轻浮的想法。
It's the opposite.
正相反。
In my native language, that is Italian,
在我的母语，意大利语中，
"beautiful" is "bello."
"美丽“ 是”Bello“。
In Spanish, "beauty" is "belleza."
在西班牙语中， ”美丽“是”belleza "。
In Greek, "beautiful" is "kalos."
在希腊语中，“美丽”是“kalos”。
When you add "agathos," that means "beautiful and good."
当你加上“agathos"， 它的意思就是”美丽和美好"。
In no one of those languages, "beautiful" just means "beautiful."
但是在这些语言中， 美丽的意思不仅仅是美丽。
It also means "good."
同时也是美好的意思。
Real beauty is when the invisible
真正的美是无形与有形的结合，
joins the visible, coming on surface.
并呈现于事物的表面。
And this doesn't apply only to art or nature.
这不仅是在艺术和自然中适用。
This applies to science, human curiosity, solidarity --
同时也适用于科学， 人类的好奇心，团结心——
that's the reason why you may say,
这也是为什么你可能会说，
"This is a beautiful person,"
“这是个美丽的人”，
"That's a beautiful mind."
“这是美丽的灵魂”。
This, this is the beauty that can change people
这种美可以把一个人变成
into better people,
更好的人，
by switching a special light in their eyes.
改变他们眼中的亮光。
And making buildings for this beauty
然后为这种美打造建筑，
makes cities better places to live.
使城市成为更好的居住地。
And better cities
更好的城市
make better citizens.
会孕育出更好的居民。
Well, this beauty --
这种美——
this universal beauty, I should say --
这普适的美，我应该这么说——
is one of the few things that can change the world.
是极少的可以 改变世界的事情之一。
Believe me, this beauty will save the world.
相信我， 这种美将会拯救世界。
One person at a time, but it will do it.
慢慢来， 但是终将会发生的。
Thank you.
谢谢。
(Applause)
（鼓掌）